[man]
Boy! The tide is on the turn!
I'm not warning you again!
[boy] Ships! There!
Danes... The devil's turds.
Are they traders?
No. They come as Vikings.
We go!
Go! Go!
[all grunting]
Where's my son?
Uhtred, take a half-dozen men
and ride to the river.
There are Pagans there, you watch
them, see how many they are!
-Of course, Father.
-Do nothing more. You understand?
-Yes, Father.
-Oswart, what is it?
Ships!
I saw them first from the beach.
-What ships?
-Danes.
They're heading for the river!
[gasps]
Oh, God and his saints
preserve us, they have no soul.
-We must pray.
-We must act.
Uhtred, do not fight them,
not a single one.
-Be back by night fall.
-Yes, Father.
They are sent by God
to punish us for our sins.
Our sins be damned, they are here to
support the Viking army in Eoferwic.
You must instruct the priest
to pray for our deliverance.
-Alferic!
-Lord?
Get them inside!
We take in as many
women and elders as we can,
and the rest to higher
ground and out of sight.
Send word to rouse the country.
I want every man
inside this fortress.
And every man
must be prepared to die.
[wind whistling]
-[man] Port side ready to row!
-[man 2] Port side ready to row!
-Starboard side ready to row!
[men grunting]
Father.
-[men grunting]
-[man orders, indistinct]
Taste.
[indistinct]
-Fresh.
-Sweet water.
-Yes.
-What else do you see?
[exhales] I see a clear river,
fish as big as a man's leg.
I see a forest alive with meat,
and more than that, I see
a place to grow fat and old.
[horses whinny]
Horses.
Yeah, and I see spies,
shitting themselves.
[men] Yeah!
[men yelling indistinct]
We'll meet sword with sword!
You are pagans!
We have the greater god
on our side!
Kjartan, I think we should
teach that boy a lesson.
-Taking her in. At speed.
-[man] Take her to speed!
[men grunting]
[baby crying]
[man yells indistinct]
Why do I leave the villages
unprotected, and bring the men inside?
Is that your question?
A village can be rebuilt,
a warrior can die only once.
The Danes maybe
heading south to Eoferwic.
But they will kill
whoever they can on the way.
Now go find the priest.
Yes, Father.
[man] Come in, Osbert,
don't skulk in the shadows.
He, uh, wants to know
if you're ready?
Almost. Do you know
what I am tasked with?
Um, a letter?
A response to a letter,
this letter, from King Aella,
asking your father
for his support; his army,
to help recapture
the City of Eoferwic.
This is why it is important for
you to be able to read and write.
Father can't read nor write.
Yeah, well, for your father
it's too late.
King Aella could have
sent a man on horseback.
Yeah, but who's to say the man
on horseback speaks the truth?
Or has remembered
the true message?
What these letters will
represent is history; facts...
Your father is informing
King Aella, and King Osbert,
he will be alongside
their armies at Eoferwic.
And the mark of Bebbanburg
will guarantee the truth of it.
Why do we fight for Eoferwic?
Well, we fight for Eoferwic because
we do not wish to see England,
piece-by-piece,
become Daneland.
[chuckles]
I heard it said that we
were Pagans once;
that Woden and Odin
are the same.
We saw the error of our ways
and we looked to Rome.
I heard the Pagans
have fierce Gods of War.
Well, we are right
and they are mistaken.
Osbert, we are blessed.
I should make you swear
on St. Cuthbert's comb
never to mention
the likes of Woden again.
But what if I had
a hound called Woden?
What if I didn't,
what would you do then?
-You haven't, you have not!
-What would you do then?
What if you had
a pig called, Thor?
Come; let's go
see your father? Come!
A pig called, Thor...
Is it really
St. Cuthbert's comb?
Of course,
it's St. Cuthbert's comb,
and his holy hair
lies in the teeth of the comb.
Where was your father last?
He was humping the servant girl.
-That's a lie, Osbert.
-No.
Are you never
gonna tire of teasing?
Nope!
[man] Horsemen approaching!
He rides Uhtred's horse.
Osbert?!
No!
[yells]
Bury what's left of him.
[panting]
Osbert. Come on...
Remind me of the last words
I spoke to him.
You told him to watch,
do not fight.
We have no idea
of the circumstance--
-Do not fight, means do not fight.
-He was young.
There was no fight
to be had until Eoferwic.
You wanted to see Osbert,
my Lord.
You...
You are now called Uhtred.
Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
-You have your stone, the amber?
-Yes, Father.
The priest will show you
your history, the parchments.
Make him understand who he is.
[priest] Lord, I... I should
like to baptize him again.
Well, if he arrives
at Heavens gate as Uhtred,
they may wonder
what's happened to Osbert.
Do what you must,
but do as I ask.
Lord.
We were kings here once, boy!
Kings of all the lands between
the Rivers Tuede and Tine.
And we should be kings again.
Yes, we should,
but it doesn't matter
what they call us,
so long as they obey.
Our ancestors took this land, and it has
been strengthened with our blood and bone.
And now you are the new heir
of Bebbanburg, do you hear me?
And you will
die for it if needed.
Yes, Father.
And I will give you the head
of the man
who killed Uhtred.
No, you are Uhtred!
Have you not been
listening to me!
Do not tell me what it is you
will do, you are just a pup!
You will give me nothing, you
will watch and you will learn!
Put him in the water before his
mother's tongue gives me grief.
She's not my mother.
Will you take him with you to battle
to watch and learn? He's old enough.
I need you to choose 30 men
and remain here at Bebbanburg.
Protect the boy,
he is the heir.
Thirty will hold
and is few enough to feed.
Will you do this for me?
I'd rather
be with you at Eoferwic,
-but I'll do as you ask.
-Thank you.
[indistinct chatter]
Come on, quickly.
Up there, go on.
[man] Hurry, please.
[shivering]
Heavenly Father,
receive your servant, Uhtred,
into the Holy kind of the Saints
and into the ranks
of the most bright angels.
Let your holy waters cleanse him and
make him worthy of your blessing.
Make him your instrument
and your rod.
Let him realize the significance
of the written word
so that he may
learn of your glory
and in turn,
may spread your word.
[water bubbling]
-Beo--
-Let him grow in wisdom
and in respect, so he may
lead in a Godly manner.
Beocca he's cleansed.
Amen.
[gasps]
Uhtred, son of
Uhtred of Bebbanburg,
welcome to
the Christian world.
Behold your people
and your lands.
[cheering]
[birds squawking]
[footsteps approaching]
Where are the people,
the soldiers?
On the road to Eoferwic;
led by your father.
He will join the two other
kings of Northumbria.
With... Without me?
You are to remain at Bebbanburg
with your kindly uncle.
I am sworn to keep you safe.
Should you wish to fight
we can always arm-wrestle.
-Where's the priest?
-With your father. Eat.
You have work to do,
Uhtred, in the stables;
Thankfully,
we have been left horses.
-You should eat.
-I'm not hungry.
We have work to do,
horse shit to shovel.
Come and find me
when you've finished.
[door shuts]
Scallion, if my brother falls
in battle, the boy must fall.
[indistinct chatter]
[man coughing]
[dog barking]
All this way
and no reception party.
Earl Ragnar.
Guthrum!
-How are you?
-I'm fine, I'm hungry!
-And your boy?
-He's coming.
-Ragnar.
-Ubba, I brought men and horses.
Good to see you, are you well?
[men laughing]
You made a gift of his own son's
head? How did this Lord react?
He did nothing.
He brought his warriors into the
fortress and kept them inside.
It was not cowardice.
Restraint.
He is saving his men.
That man is Uhtred.
One of the three kings
of Northumbria, a warrior king.
The other two are fools, they would
rather be here fighting each other.
This is true?
King Aella
and King Osbert, they, uh,
both lay claim to Eoferwic.
They have
the strangest of names.
-[chuckles]
-So, when do we fight?
Soon, I hope.
I am still to decide.
Fools or not,
they have three armies.
-They have numbers.
-[Ragnar] But are divided.
Three kings, but only one who
can lead them, this Uhtred...
Then we kill him and Northumbria
is ours, all of it.
[laughing]
Listen to him, listen to the
boy, he reminds me of me!
Yeah, when you were younger.
Of course, when I was younger.
He's just a boy.
-Just saying.
-Ubba, did you say I was old?
-Storri? I'm not getting old.
-No.
Ubba, I have seen
the land outside the city.
I have a plan in mind,
a good plan.
And my son would like
to wet his sword, with you.
So do we fight?
Storri?
The signs are good.
Only this morning I saw a raven,
flying towards the Saxon camp,
and he was asking me to follow,
I'm sure of it.
Hmm...
[whispering indistinct]
Then we fight.
[men cheering]
[Osbert]
What kind of hell is this?
It's a Pagan's hell.
We out number them!
But there are more,
there must be...
Nothing changes,
we attack with half our number,
the second half have to follow,
once we have
the measure of them.
They have conceded
to higher ground.
Kingaler,
yours and Lord Uhtred's armies
will attack in the first wave.
Prepare! Prepare!
[horns blow]
Shield!
No... No, not without me!
Come night fall,
we'll be rid of this plague
and counting our share
of the plunder!
[all yelling]
My shield!
[all whispering indistinct]
[whispering stops]
Kill them all!
[all yelling]
[grunting]
[Aella] The wall is holding.
Go! Transfer all
your shield and drive!
Drive!
Ease.
Ease!
Push! Keep pushing!
It's working!
Drive them!
[screaming]
[Beocca] They are tiring,
they can't fight back.
-We're winning, look.
-[man] We're winning...
[yells indistinct]
Not yet! Not yet!
Dear God, no...
[all yelling]
Shield! Wall!
[chanting]
Dear God, of infinite mercy,
not this!
Kill them all!
[screams]
Legs! Legs!
Legs protect your legs!
Lift up your sword
and spare these men of England
who fight in your name.
Let the heathens hearts
crumble and wither.
Bestow your power
upon these men of England,
so they can glorify your name
with the blood of the devils.
Have mercy now lord,
do not forsake us,
do not forsake England.
Follow me! Follow me!
Take him!
[grunting]
[Ragnar] Close the sealed wall!
Close the wall and take him!
[gasps]
No!
[yelling]
He's like a wasp.
-The wasp has lost its sting.
-Yeah.
[yelling]
[groans]
[panting]
Are you sure he's a Saxon?
He fights like a Dane.
Yeah.
[grunting]
[indistinct chatter]
[dog barking]
[woman screaming]
[screaming]
Leave her!
She is to live!
Some of these young ones
can come in useful.
Father,
there's the boy I spoke of.
The one who almost killed you?
And you're leaving him with me?
I've never seen a man
get the better of you yet.
[all cheering]
[woman screaming]
Cut me some chicken.
Careful, the blade is sharp.
It can kill a man.
The chicken is on your platter.
Have you always been blind?
Oh, I see enough.
So... who have
they been killing below?
[woman screaming]
Prisoners...
Just now a king.
-Did he die well?
-No.
Then he shouldn't
have been king.
Tell me, who sits
in the middle of the hall?
[yells]
Is it a big man
and a small man?
Yes, and a gray man
sits in between them.
If you get to live, you should
beware of the big man: Ubba.
My advice for you is
to never cross Ubba
and never, never fight him.
If I get to live?
He listens to no one
but the Gods.
Men who take their orders from
the Gods are unpredictable.
What did you mean?
When you said if I get to live?
You're my prisoner.
The gray man will be Egbert,
he's a Saxon Aelderman.
He has pledged allegiance
and now he calls himself a king.
He is king of nothing.
Soon all of the kings in England
shall be kings of nothing.
Northumbria's ours,
Mercia will soon by ours.
Then East Anglia, Cornwallum
and then the greatest prize
is the last kingdom: Wessex.
I've heard of Wessex.
Anything will grow in Wessex.
[men groan]
Tell me your name.
Uhtred... I am
the Aelderman of Bebbanburg.
You are?
I am...
I own lands to the north.
How long have you been
the Aelderman of these lands?
Your father chose to fight us.
And is now... dead.
He...
He was not fond of me.
I now understand why
my son spared you...
...Uhtred of Bebbanburg,
you are a warrior.
Have some ale.
Drink it...
...lots of it.
Here.
Take it up there.
[clanging]
I am thinking
of keeping them both,
the boy and the girl;
they can help your mother.
Disagree?
No, but we did
kill his father.
And if he is an Aelderman,
we could sell him for a ransom.
Perhaps.
[gasps softly]
[water sloshing]
Brida, be careful
not to spill the water,
you'll turn the floor to mud.
Uhtred,
wood needs to be chopped.
Brida, you can do the goats.
Will there be time
for Uhtred to play?
Only when work is done.
I don't like our daughter
having to play with the slaves.
-They're only children.
-They have a place.
Grumpy...
[man] My horse.
Hey, Ragnar Ragnarson!
Hey, Uhtred of wherever.
How about you teach me
how to use a sword.
We don't teach slaves
how to fight.
That tongue of yours
will be your death boy.
Now get back to work!
What does the play involve?
We built a hall in the Gorge.
I'm a mistress,
Uhtred is a warrior.
-Not a servant?
-It is a game.
[giggling]
-[Uhtred] A wolf?
-[Brida] Uhtred!
-That was it, a wolf.
-Boar watch out!
I saw it, it's sharp teeth
and yellow eyes.
Don't let the wolves
get to me Uhtred.
Use the fire to keep them away.
I see them. They are as big
as Ubba and smell worse.
[chuckles]
Did you see that?
[twig snaps]
[girl] Uhtred?
Stay up there.
[gasps] Look!
Uhtred, what is happening?
Stay up there, Thyra.
It's Sven, he won't hurt you.
[Brida] But he'll kill us.
[yelling]
He will kill us! Run!
That was a real sword!
I saw it.
[Thyra screams]
-Uhtred! Uhtred!
-Thyra.
[gasps]
[yelling]
What's this?
You been fighting again?
Yes.
With Sven?
Kjartan's son?
Yes.
Uhtred,
he's much bigger than you.
-He's a turd.
-Why do you say that?
[man]
Who started it?
-Who began the fight?
-I began the fight.
For no other reason
than that he's a turd?
Danes have murdered for less.
[woman]
Uhtred, that's enough!
-You want to be sold boy?
-I wish to eat.
-[man] Speak up.
-I wish to eat!
You want to eat?
You know what?
I say you starve.
Fighting is expected,
disobedience is not.
[slapping]
[grunts]
Sven began the fight!
Kjartan! Kjartan!
Earl Ragnar, let me first say,
he's a... he's a good boy.
He brought this sword on to my
land. I will have words with him.
In time, he'll serve
on your ship. He... he...
He has offended me.
He will honor you
and he meant no harm, Lord.
He meant no harm?
He looked
at my daughter's nakedness.
And he was punished.
Your Saxon slave cut him.
Shall I make
a square of branches?
Are you gonna fight me
for your son or fetch him?
Sven! Come out here.
Tell him what you have to say.
-I'm sorry.
-He can't hear you.
I'm sorry, Lord,
for what I did.
You laid hands on my daughter.
You stripped her naked.
-Half-naked, Lord.
-He is at an age, Lord.
-Is this true, half-naked?
-Yes, Lord.
[exhales]
Then I shall only
take his one eye.
[Kjartan]
No, Lord, please!
[grunting]
Kjartan, you are
banished from my land.
[groaning in pain]
[fire cackling]
I have something for you.
What is it?
An amulet; Thor's hammer.
Ah, but, um...
But what?
You're Christian.
Take it.
-I can't.
-Don't you want it?
-I... I do want it!
-Take it!
-I'm trying.
-[grunts]
-I don't think he wants it.
-I... I do want it!
-No, I don't think so.
Thank you.
Tell me about Denmark...
...your home.
What can I say about Denmark?
It's wet.
And harsh... and the ground
is so flat and sandy
you can't grow a fart.
Which is why
we are here in England.
To grow.
And why young Ragnar
will soon be going for Ireland.
You leave to fight?
To make my wealth.
If you want land or silver
you have to take it.
You made me...
proud today... Uhtred...
You made me proud.
[birds squawking]
[Alferic] I don't know you, you don't
have the appearance of a messenger
and Ubba's payments not yet due.
No, Lord, I was a ship's master.
Ah, well I have no ships,
I need no ship's master.
I have news
that you will want to hear.
Well...
I would want something
in return, Lord.
[scoffs]
Not now, not quite.
But perhaps we could continue
to help each other.
Perhaps.
Two days south of here.
This little rat with the man I used
to serve until he banished me.
He has a slave, treats him well.
This is a slave you are entitled
to buy back if you wish to.
Buy back?
It's your nephew, Uhtred,
Lord. He lives.
[men talking indistinct]
[Uhtred] What if I'm
against being ransomed?
Your family has discovered
that you're still alive,
and they wish for you to be
returned; but they must pay.
Pay Ragnar?
Ubba takes more than half.
It's normal.
But I have no family.
Keep them over there,
tether the horses.
Scallion, here.
Uhtred.
Are they treating you well?
I am fed, yes.
Good, good.
That's all we ask.
And what is this around
your neck, some symbol?
Oh, this...
They make me wear it.
May I see it?
Look, I will speak plainly;
your uncle will kill you.
Right, you can not go back to
Bebbanburg, you must escape.
He wants to be the Aelderman;
he wants to be a king, in fact,
like the pathetic
Egbert over there.
A puppet king for his
Danish masters.
You should go to Wessex.
King Aethelred,
real King Aethelred
and his brother,
the Prince Alfred:
they are good men,
good Christian men.
[Ragnar] That is enough
whispering in his ear, priest.
-Uhtred.
-One more word and I'll have your ball-bag for a purse.
[whispering]
I will meet you there.
[normal voice]
That will not be necessary.
What did he say?
He... He asked if you were
treating me well.
-How much?
-Three hundred.
That is a ridiculous amount.
How can a boy be worth
300 pieces of silver?
Because I say so, because
he is a Lord, an Aelderman.
He is a boy.
I am the Aelderman
of Bebbanburg.
I carry the seal
and the banner.
That seal is my father's,
which is now mine!
You will be silent.
You are for sale, nothing more.
-For ransom, Lord.
-That's is what I said.
My Lords,
I have given up land, horses;
I have offered a generous supply
of food as well as my sword.
All I ask in return is a
fair price for my only nephew.
[man] What would you say
is a fair price?
[Alferic] I will offer
100 pieces of silver.
[man] Two hundred.
My allegiance and 100 pieces
is surely a fair price.
[man] It is not.
I will give 120 pieces
of silver for the boy.
[man chuckles]
Not enough!
Very well, 200 pieces.
I agree to your terms.
[whispering indistinct]
The boy's sold to Earl Ragnar.
-What?
-Ransomed, Lord!
That's what I said!
So the matter is closed!
My Lords,
I have come a long way.
I have offered my allegiance.
Which is why you are
allowed to breathe.
If you have an
argument it's with me now.
If business is done,
we have ale to drink.
And King Egbert needs to sit.
[laughing]
[Uhtred]
Am I not for ransom anymore?
[Ragnar]
You heard Ubba, I bought you.
I thought I might
sacrifice you to Odin.
You bought me for how much?
-Too much.
-How much is too much?
My swords weight in silver.
I agree, I may have been robbed,
but we like you boy,
we're going to keep you.
Does this mean I'm a Dane?
It means is that you are Uhtred
Ragnarson. You are a son to me now.
[yelps]
Brida, not that way!
Take the goat out the side.
Next time, I promise!
Mother, look!
It's beautiful, it really is.
I can't believe
I'm loosing you already!
I will be
living across the field.
And if he does not treat you well, you just
come marching right back across that field.
Oh, look at this place...
Uhtred, do you like
my wedding necklace?
I do, very pretty.
He doesn't know
anything about necklaces.
You might as well ask me.
Uhtred, with me; you can help me
slaughter the goats.
I've only just washed.
[chuckles]
The goats will be pleased.
Later you can sweep the floor.
[gasps]
[laughing]
Move over!
This is an excuse to talk,
that's all.
With Thyra to be married; maybe it's
time you got together with Brida.
There are men, good men,
asking about her.
So you have to decide what you are
to her, what you are to each other.
[chuckling]
Brida has her own mind.
She has... but I see
the way she looks at you.
She's watching the charcoal
tonight in the woods.
Take my horse and join her.
-The earth will be warm.
-[laughing]
Why not?
I just thought in order to be a
real Dane I had to marry a Dane.
[sighs]
Come on.
I love you
like I love young Ragnar.
[indistinct chatter]
What are you doing here?
[breathing heavily]
[moaning]
[both giggling]
Do you ever think of
your English life?
Who you were
before we came to Ragnar?
No.
Do you?
-I think of who I--
-Shh!
[men whispering]
Voices...
Men below.
Danes. Who are they?
[man whispers]
This way...
That's Kjartan!
Remember him?
That must be Sven.
This is wrong.
We need to tell Ragnar.
They are between us
and the wall.
Then we go up and around,
we leave the horses and run.
[whispering] In front of
the door. That's it!
[dog barking]
Ragnar, smoke!
Fire!
Hoo-rah! Wake up!
...wake up! Fire!
[screaming]
[Ragnar]
Come on! come on!
[man] This way. Ravn!
Come. Come quickly.
Come!
[coughing]
-The door is blocked!
-So is this one!
Be ready.
[screaming]
This one's open,
this one's open!
come on, follow me. This way.
[screaming]
[speaks indistinct]
[man] Archers!
Don't go up there, wait for me!
Come. Come!
Ragnar!
Close the doors,
we have Thyra,
Let the rest burn.
[grunts]
Take her with you to Valhalla.
-Yes.
-I will meet you there.
[yelling]
[grunting]
[screaming]
Oh, no...
Find the silver!
Now!
[men speaking indistinct]
They're searching
for Ragnar's wealth.
They'll never find it.
Search in the back!
Come on, were leaving soon.
You thought I'd let you
marry someone else.
But... do you know what I will
do with this body...
...this mouth?
I will do all I have
dreamt of... and more.
And who will call a halt?
Earl Ragnar the fearless,
is gone.
And with him, Uhtred,
his Saxon pet;
a pile of ashes.
Anything.
Get down!
Look at that man, the Saxon.
His name is Scallion.
He works with my uncle.
He'll tell him that I'm dead.
-Let him do it.
-I see him with Kjartan.
[Kjartan] Burn it to the ground.
[Brida] He and your uncle,
maybe they're in it together?
And what makes them believe they
can do this without punishment?
Shh! They will be punished,
but not by you.
Uhtred, listen to me, we serve Ragnar
best alive, we tell the story.
-I need to kill someone.
-No.
And I choose him.
Uhtred, no!
Come on!
[men yelling indistinct]
[sighs]
[laughing]
[Kjartan] The main thing is to
keep the horses together, yeah.
Don't leave any weapons behind.
Move those over
and we'll look in the back.
Don't leave anything in there
just bring it all out.
[pants]
-Yeah, come on.
-[man] Over here!
OK, come on.
[grunts]
You know who I am,
it's me your looking for.
[blade pierces skin]
[grimaces]
It's me your looking for.
You remember me?
[groans]
[panting]
-There's no more! We are going.
-Come on.
Bring the horses.
[sobs]
[grunts]
By right,
it belongs to young Ragnar.
Yes...
But we spend what we need
to spend; we stay alive.
We tell the story and then what?
We find a new Lord to serve.
I will not stand by and have
everything that is mine taken from me.
I'm going back....
Where?
To the beginning.
[horn blows]
-Is it Scallion?
-No, my Lord.
-He looks like a Dane.
-Could be one of Kjartan's men.
I am Uhtred of Bebbanburg,
and I shall take what is mine!
Bebbanburg is mine!
Horses!